<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2015, Andrew Lindesay
Distributed under the terms of the MIT License.
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" xml:id="userrating">

    <title>User Rating</title>

    <para>
        A &quot;user rating&quot; is an opinion given by a user of the application-server system about a particular
        version of a package.  The user rating contains optional details such as;
    </para>

    <para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>A comment</listitem>
            <listitem>A rating from zero to five</listitem>
            <listitem>
                A stability value;
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Will not start up (nostart)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Very unstable (veryunstable)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Unstable but usable (unstablebutusable)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Mostly stable (mostlystable)</listitem>
                    <listitem>Stable (stable)</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
        The user rating is always given in the context of a specific package version even though, from the user's
        perspective, it may apply to the package as a whole.  This is important to give context to the user rating.
        It is naturally still possible to view all of the user ratings for all or some package versions of a package.
    </para>

    <para>
        User ratings' aggregates are considered in the context of a single repository.
    </para>

    <para>
        A user rating is also associated with a &quot;natural language&quot; such as English, German or Japanese so
        that the language of the comment (if present) can be know.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Package Rating Derivation</title>

        <para>
            After some time, a number of users may have submitted user ratings.  After there are sufficient ratings
            to reach or exceed a sample size minimum, it is possible to derive a rating for the package as a
            whole --- an aggregate.  If the situation is such that there are an insufficient number of user
            ratings then the package does not have a rating.  In regard to API responses, this situation will
            yield a &quot;null&quot; value for a package's rating.  A minimum value can be configured (see
            <link linkend="config">here</link>) to define this minimum sample size.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Finding Ratings for the Derivation</title>

        <para>
            User ratings are only considered for a &quot;number of versions back&quot; up to the present.  The
            number of versions back is able to be configured (see <link linkend="config">here</link>).  In deciding
            what constitutes a prior version only the following elements of the version identity are considered;
        </para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>major</listitem>
                <listitem>minor</listitem>
                <listitem>micro</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            There is also no consideration of architecture in relation to the &quot;numer of versions back&quot;.
        </para>

        <para>
            For each user who has submitted a user rating, the user ratings are sorted by;
        </para>

        <para>
            <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
                <listitem>
                    package version
                    <footnote><para>The ordering semantics are the same as the C++ code in Haiku</para></footnote>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>create timestamp</listitem>
                <listitem>architecture</listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            This provides a total ordering on the user ratings.  Only the <emphasis>last</emphasis> user rating is
            considered from this user.  All of the users' user ratings are collected in this way to provide a set
            of user ratings.
        </para>

        <para>
            Taking an example,
            <footnote><para>Note that this data forms the basis for the main-flow automated testing.</para></footnote>
            suppose that we have the following table of package versions (major . minor . micro . revision) and
            user ratings;
        </para>

        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="7">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Version</entry>
                        <entry>Architecture</entry>
                        <entry>User 1</entry>
                        <entry>User 2</entry>
                        <entry>User 3</entry>
                        <entry>User 4</entry>
                        <entry>User 5</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>0.0.9</entry>
                        <entry>x86</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry>2</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>1.0.0</entry>
                        <entry>x86</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry>2 &#x2606;</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>1.0.1</entry>
                        <entry>x86</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry>1 &#x2606;</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>1.0.1.1</entry>
                        <entry>x86</entry>
                        <entry>3</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>1.0.2</entry>
                        <entry>x86</entry>
                        <entry>4</entry>
                        <entry>3 &#x2606;</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>1.0.2</entry>
                        <entry>x86_64</entry>
                        <entry>1 &#x2606;</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        <para>
            In the case of User 1 who has submitted multiple user ratings, the order of input is;
        </para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>1.0.1.1</listitem>
                <listitem>1.0.2 (x86)</listitem>
                <listitem>1.0.2 (x86_64)</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            In this case, with a &quot;versions back&quot; configured as 2, only user ratings that are associated
            with versions equal to or greater than 1.0.0 will be considered.  This is because, according to the
            algorithm, the prior versions are 1.0.2, 1.0.1 and 1.0.0 and two back from the current version of 1.0.2
            yields 1.0.0.
        </para>

        <para>
            The rating values which are shown with the &quot;&#x2606;&quot; symbol are the set of rating values that will
            be used to aggregate a rating value for the package.  With the &quot;minimum number of ratings&quot;
            configured to 3, a rating could be derived for this package because there are enough samples; it
            would be 1.75.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Triggering Derived Rating Calculations</title>

        <para>
            Each time a user rating is persisted, the derived rating for the package is calculated.  This mechanic
            utilizes the ORM's &quot;listener&quot; architecture and is driven by the class
            &quot;UserRatingDerivationTriggerListener&quot;.  In a situation of high-load, the system will prevent
            excess pressure by queuing the derivations.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Storage of the Sample Size</title>

        <para>
            The number of user ratings used to derive a given rating for a package is stored as well as the rating
            on the &quot;Pkg&quot; entity.
        </para>
    </section>

</chapter>