<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2019, Andrew Lindesay
Distributed under the terms of the MIT License.
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" xml:id="datahandling">

    <title>Data Handling</title>

    <para>
        This section covers how data is handled in Haiku Depot Server (HDS) in
        terms of its use and persistence from a user perspective.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Browser</title>
        <para>
            A Browser is a piece of software that can be run on a computing
            device in order to view web sites and web applications.  HDS is such
            a web application.  Browsers such as
            <ulink url="https://www.mozilla.org/firefox/">Firefox</ulink>
            and
            <ulink url="https://www.google.com/chrome/">Google Chrome</ulink>
            can be used to access HDS and as it does so, there is the
            possibility that some data may be stored in the Browser.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Tracking</title>
            <para>
                HDS does not use a form of tracking technology with
                third-parties.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Cookies</title>
            <para>
                HDS does not use Cookie technology.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Local Storage</title>
            <para>
                Local Storage is a mechanism that is available in some Browsers
                for maintaining data in the Browser.  HDS can optionally use
                local storage for conveniently storing some data for the user.
                Using the Browser's Local Storage is optional and the user is
                given the choice to allow or disallow HDS to use Local Storage.
                The HDS system is entirely functional without using Local
                Storage, but some aspects may not be as convenient.
                The data stored by HDS using Local Storage includes the
                following at the time of writing;
            </para>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        The user of the Browser's preferred natural language
                        such as English or Russian.
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        If applicable, the user's current authentication.  This
                        is convenient because the authentication is then able,
                        for a short time, survive a Browser restart and is also
                        able to be shared between tabs of the same Browser.
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        Some user selections related to search.  For example,
                        the user's selection of repositories.  This is more
                        convenient because the user does not need to re-select
                        their repositories each time they open a new HDS Browser
                        window.
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

</chapter>