<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  ~ Copyright 2018, Andrew Lindesay
  ~ Distributed under the terms of the MIT License.
  -->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" xml:id="config">

    <title>Configuration</title>

    <section>
        <title>Application</title>

        <para>
            The application server is configured using a standard java properties file.  This same format is used in
            different ways for either an actual deployment or a development environment.
        </para>

        <para>
            A typical java properties file has the following general form;
        </para>

        <para>
            <programlisting># Comment
key1=value1
key2=value2</programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>
            There are a number of keys which are described below.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="config-general">
            <title>General</title>

            <section>
                <title>architecture.default.code</title>
                <para>
                    This configuration setting defines the code of the default architecture that should be shown.
                    Example values might be &quot;x86_gcc2&quot; or &quot;ppc&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>deployment.isproduction</title>
                <para>
                    This configuration setting can have a value of &quot;true&quot; or &quot;false&quot;.  When false,
                    the system will display a warning message on the user interface to indicate that the deployment
                    is non-production.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>pkgversion.viewcounter.protectrecurringincrementfromsameclient</title>
                <para>
                    This configuration setting can have a value of &quot;true&quot; or &quot;false&quot;.  When true
                    (the default), the system will make basic efforts to protect against one client repeatedly
                    incrementing a package version's view counter.  This might happen when a user navigates
                    to view a package and then navigates away and back again.  With this value set as true, within
                    a window of time, these two visits would be considered to be the same in terms of incrementing
                    the view counter.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="config-general-hvif2png">
                <title>hvif2png.path</title>
                <para>
                    This is a system path to the
                    <link linkend="overview-prerequisites-hvif2png">hvif2png</link> tool.
                    This tool is used to render HVIF icon data to PNG images that can be displayed on the web
                    site.  This value is optional, but if absent, no icons for packages will shown.  Instead,
                    placebo icons will be displayed.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>optipng.path</title>
                <para>
                    This is a system path to the
                    <ulink url="http://optipng.sourceforge.net/">OptiPNG</ulink> tool.
                    This tool can be used in some situations to optimize PNG data; for example when configuring
                    icons for packages.  An example value might be &quot;/usr/local/bin/optipng&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>desktop.application.version.min</title>
                <para>
                    This optional value can be configured to specify a minimum version value for the
                    HaikuDepot desktop application.  If a version of the desktop application attempts to
                    communicate with the server with a version lower than this value then the server
                    will return a 412 (precondition failed) HTTP status and a header that describes the
                    minimum version required.
                </para>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Package Rating Derivation</title>

            <para>
                See
                <link linkend="userrating">the user rating chapter</link>
                for further details on how the package rating derivation algorithm uses these values to calculate
                packages' ratings.
            </para>

            <section>
                <title>userrating.aggregation.pkg.versionsback</title>
                <para>
                    This value is the number of versions back in the past from which the derivation will consider
                    user ratings.  This value defaults to 2.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>userrating.aggregation.pkg.minratings</title>
                <para>
                    When deriving an aggregate rating for a package, if there are not enough user ratings then the
                    package will have no rating.  This value is the minimum threshold and has a default value of 3.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Database and Data Related</title>

            <section>
                <title>jdbc.driver</title>
                <para>
                    This is the class name of the JDBC driver employed.  The value should be
                    &quot;org.postgresql.Driver&quot;
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>jdbc.url</title>
                <para>
                    This is the JDBC connect URL to the main database.  The value should be of the form
                    &quot;jdbc:postgresql://localhost:5432/haikudepotserver&quot;
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>jdbc.username</title>
                <para>
                    This is the database username.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>jdbc.password</title>
                <para>
                    This is the database password.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>flyway.migrate</title>
                <para>
                    Set this to &quot;true&quot; if you would like database schema migrations to be applied
                    automatically as necessary.  Generally this should be configured to &quot;true&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>flyway.validateOnMigrate</title>
                <para>
                    Set this to &quot;false&quot; if you want the system to validate schema migrations.  This can
                    be helpful at development time when the schema is in flux, but should be &quot;true&quot; in
                    production.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>flyway.validateOnMigrate</title>
                <para>
                    Set this to &quot;false&quot; if you want the system to validate schema migrations.  This can
                    be helpful at development time when the schema is in flux, but should be &quot;true&quot; in
                    production.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>cayenne.query.cache.size</title>
                <para>
                    Cayenne is the ORM system behind this application.  Some queries' results are cached and
                    this configuration item allows the size of the query cache to be configured.
                </para>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Web-Related</title>

            <section>
                <title>jawr.debug.on</title>
                <para>
                    This configuration relates to the
                    <ulink url="https://jawr.java.net/">JAWR</ulink>
                    debug setting.  It will default to &quot;false&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>baseurl</title>
                <para>
                    This is the base URL used to formulate URLs to be sent out that can be used to return back to the
                    system.
                </para>
                <para>
                    For example; this might be used to create the URL used to manage the password reset process.  The
                    URL base is included in the email body to users who have requested a password-reset.  This has to
                    be configured because the application itself does not know the path by which the HTTP request had
                    reached it.
                </para>
                <para>
                    In the case of a development environment, this base URL might be something like
                    &quot;http://localhost:8080&quot;
                </para>
                <para>
                    Note that this value should have no trailing slash.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Token Bearer Authentication</title>

            <para>
                You can find out more about the token-bearer authentication system
                <link linkend="security-authentication-tokenbearer">here</link>.
            </para>

            <section>
                <title>authentication.jws.sharedkey</title>
                <para>
                    This shared key is used to sign the authentication tokens transmitted between the server and the
                    client.  This value is optional.  If it is not supplied then a random shared key will be used for
                    each launch of the application server.  Non-configured keys will not work where two or more
                    load-balanced application servers are employed.  Any random value can be used for this and a possible
                    way to create values is to use the command &quot;uuidgen&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>authentication.jws.issuer</title>
                <para>
                    This identifies the system that has produced a given token and is required.  It should be a string
                    with the suffix &quot;.hds&quot;.  For example &quot;staging.hds&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>authentication.jws.expiryseconds</title>
                <para>
                    This configuration value defines how many seconds a token will be able to be used before it expires.
                    This value is optional and a sensible default will be employed in its absence.
                </para>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Email</title>

            <para>
                You can find out more about the email system
                <link linkend="architecture-applicationserverinfrastructure-email">here</link>.
            </para>

            <section>
                <title>smtp.host</title>
                <para>
                    The host name or IP address of the SMTP server.  This configuration value is required.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>smtp.port</title>
                <para>
                    The port of the SMTP server.  This configuration value is optional and will default to 25.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>smtp.auth</title>
                <para>
                    Possible values are &quot;true&quot; or &quot;false&quot;.  When true, SMTP authentication will be
                    used.  This configuration value is optional and will default to &quot;false&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>smtp.username</title>
                <para>
                    This is only required when SMTP authentication is configured.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>smtp.password</title>
                <para>
                    This is only required when SMTP authentication is configured.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>smtp.starttls</title>
                <para>
                    Possible values are &quot;true&quot; and &quot;false&quot;.  Configures the SMTP transport.  This
                    value is optional and defaults to &quot;false&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>email.from</title>
                <para>
                    This is the email address from which emails outbound from the system will be sent.  Typically this
                    might be a &quot;no-reply&quot; email address such as &quot;noreply@haiku-os.org&quot;.
                </para>
            </section>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Logging</title>

        <para>
            The application logging uses the
            <ulink url="http://www.slf4j.org/">SLF4J</ulink>
            logging framework.
            This is backed by the
            <ulink url="http://logback.qos.ch/">Logback</ulink>
            logging system.  When formatting log lines, it is possible to add additional meta data from the
            application server.  This is known as the &quot;MDC&quot;.  Presently supported;
        </para>

        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Key</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>authUserNickname</entry>
                        <entry>The nickname of the presently authenticated user</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>userAgent</entry>
                        <entry>The User-Agent HTTP header related to the current request</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>userAgentCode</entry>
                        <entry>This is a short code to describe the user agent in brief</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

    </section>

</chapter>