<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2019, Andrew Lindesay
Distributed under the terms of the MIT License.
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" xml:id="datahandling">

    <title>Data Handling</title>

    <para>
        This section covers how data is handled in Haiku Depot Server (HDS) in
        terms of its use, persistence and distribution from a user perspective.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Browser</title>
        <para>
            A Browser is a piece of software that can be run on a computing
            device in order to view web sites and web applications.  HDS is
            a web application.  Browsers such as
            <ulink url="https://www.mozilla.org/firefox/">Firefox</ulink>
            and
            <ulink url="https://www.google.com/chrome/">Google Chrome</ulink>
            can be used to access HDS and as it does so, there is the
            opportunity for some data to be stored in the Browser.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Tracking</title>
            <para>
                HDS does not use a form of tracking technology with
                third-parties.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Cookies</title>
            <para>
                HDS does not use Browser Cookie technology.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Local Storage</title>
            <para>
                Local Storage is a mechanism that is available in some Browsers
                for programmatically storing and later retrieving data in the
                Browser.  HDS can optionally use
                Local Storage for conveniently storing some data for the user.
                Using the Browser's Local Storage is optional and the user is
                given the choice to allow or disallow HDS to use Local Storage.
                The HDS system is functional without using Local
                Storage, but some aspects may not be as convenient; for example
                some user-preferences may not be stored across sessions.
                The data that may be stored by HDS using Local Storage
                includes the following at the time of writing;
            </para>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        The user's preferred natural language
                        such as English, French or Russian.
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        If applicable, the user's current authentication.  This
                        is convenient because the authentication is then able,
                        for a short time, to survive a Browser restart and is also
                        able to be shared between tabs of the same Browser.
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        Some user selections related to search.  For example,
                        the user's selection of repositories.  This is more
                        convenient because the user does not need to re-select
                        their repositories each time they open a new HDS Browser
                        window.
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>User Identifiers</title>
        <para>
            The user is identified in the system by short piece of text
            called a nickname.  The nickname is intended to be used to
            identify a user publicly.  For example, the nickname may be presented
            together with user-generated content to identify the author
            of the content.  HDS will publicly display and redistribute users'
            nicknames.  The user nickname is public information.
        </para>
        <para>
            The HDS system has no means of storing or working with real
            names.
        </para>
        <para>
            The user may choose to store an email address with their account.
            Some functions of the system such as being able to reset a
            user's password after a user has forgotten their password will
            not be possible without the user having supplied their email
            address.  Communication between the administrators of
            HDS and users is not possible without the user having opted to
            supply an email address.  Users' email addresses are
            intended to be private to the user and the administrators of the
            HDS system.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>User Ratings</title>
        <para>
            A user may provide ratings of their own creation in relation
            to packages within the HDS system.  Such ratings may be created
            using the web interface or through use of a provided API.  The
            information provided with a rating including any commentary is
            intended to be distributed publicly; either directly or in
            aggregate form.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Supplied Content</title>

        <para>
            Selected users are able to provide content for
            the HDS system.  This includes, but is not limited to;
        </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>Icons</listitem>
                <listitem>Screenshots</listitem>
                <listitem>Categorizations</listitem>
                <listitem>Change-logs</listitem>
                <listitem>Prominences</listitem>
                <listitem>Localizations</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            Such provided content data is assumed to be distributed as
            public domain and will be redistributed.
        </para>
    </section>

</chapter>