<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2015, Andrew Lindesay
Distributed under the terms of the MIT License.
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" xml:id="datalocalization">

    <title>Data Localization</title>

    <para>
        This section discusses the approach to localizing package data.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="datalocalization-packageversion">
        <title>Package Version Localization</title>

        <para>
            The payload of the HPKG (package binary) or HPKR (repository catalog) can contain localizations such as;
        </para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>Title</listitem>
                <listitem>Summary</listitem>
                <listitem>Description</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            These pieces of data may be conveyed in one or more languages, but data must be present for the English
            language to provide a fallback.  These localizations are effectively assigned to a specific version of
            a package because they are transported with the package data and so are referred to here are
            &quot;package version localizations&quot;.  Package version localizations are not able to be edited
            within the web application; the only means by which they can be loaded into the application is by
            importing the data from a repository.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="datalocalization-package">
        <title>Package / Fallback Localization</title>

        <para>
            A human operator is able to edit a set of localizations for an package without consideration of the
            specific version of the package.  These localizations can be provided for any language and cover the
            same items as the package version localization; title, summary and description.  A user interface is
            provided within the web application to edit these values.  These localizations are a fallback for when
            localization data is not present in the package data payload.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="datalocalization-package">
        <title>Choosing Localization Items</title>

        <para>
            For a given localization item (eg; summary) for a given package version for display purposes, the
            following precedence applies and the first non-NULL value will be used.
        </para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>The value on the package version in the user's chosen language</listitem>
                <listitem>The value on the package in the user's chosen language</listitem>
                <listitem>The value on the package version in English</listitem>
                <listitem>The value on the package in English</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

</chapter>
