<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
Copyright 2015-2017, Andrew Lindesay
Distributed under the terms of the MIT License.
-->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0" xml:id="api">

    <title>API</title>

    <section>
        <title>General</title>

        <para>
            This information applies to all areas of the API for the system; both JSON-RPC and REST packaged.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Clients</title>
            <para>
                A client of this system's API may be a desktop application (eg; Haiku Depot) or may be logic in
                a web page where the web page is using some java-script to call back to the server.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>API Version</title>
            <para>
                The application generally refers to &quot;api 1&quot; in anticipation that at some point there
                is the <emphasis>possibility</emphasis> that a second, incompatible API may be required.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Object References</title>
            <para>
                When objects such as packages or users are referred to in the API, the database primary key is
                <emphasis>not</emphasis> used.  Instead either a natural or artifical identifier is employed.  For
                example, in the case of a package, the package's name may be used.  In the case of a screen-shot,
                a GUID (unique identifier) will be used to identify a particular screenshot.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Reference Data</title>
            <para>
                Reference data means data in the application that is generally invariant.  Examples include the
                mime types, natural language, url types and so on.  In these cases, an API will generally provide
                for access to the list of reference data.  The client is expected to obtain such reference data as
                necessary and cache reference data locally.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Date and Time Data</title>
            <para>
                The system has only a concept of a &quot;moment in time&quot; which is called a timestamp.  The
                timestamp is typically communicated as the number of milliseconds elapsed since the epoc represented
                as a 64bit integer.  The timestamp communicated via the API is always relative to UTC.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Invocations and Transport</title>
            <para>
                The term &quot;invocation&quot; refers to a request-response cycle from the client software into
                the application server over the HTTP protocol.  Each API invocation is made in a
                <emphasis>stateless</emphasis> manner in that each invocation is not dependent on the prior
                invocation.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Security</title>
            <para>
                See the <link linkend="security">security</link> chapter
                for details on how to authenticate API requests as well as how API requests are authorized.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="api-ifmodifiedsince">
            <title>If-Modified-Since Header</title>
            <para>
                In order to prevent clients from downloading and processing data they already have, the client
                may add a &quot;If-Modified-Since&quot; header to the initial request.  The form of this header
                is RFC-1123 compliant and looks like &quot;Sat, 3 Dec 2016 23:48:05 GMT&quot;.  If the icon data
                has not been modified since this time, then the API will return a 304 (Not Modified) response.
            </para>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>JSON-RPC API</title>

        <para>
            Most API is vended as
            <ulink url="http://www.jsonrpc.org">JSON-RPC</ulink>
            encoded HTTP POST invocations.  The data transfer objects (DTOs) that describe the request and the
            response data as well as the APIs' interfaces exist in the &quot;haikudepotserver-api&quot; module in
            the java package; &quot;org.haiku.haikudepotserver.api1&quot;.
        </para>

        <para>
            The documentation and list of available methods can be obtained by viewing the java interfaces and
            model objects in that module.
        </para>

        <example>
            <title>Example: Get a Package using the JSON-RPC API</title>

            <para>
                In this example, the client knows the <emphasis>name</emphasis> of the package and would like
                to get the details of the package.  The java model objects that document the data required in
                request and the data that can be expected in the response can be found in the project.  The
                request model is &quot;org.haiku.haikudepotserver.api1.model.pkg.GetPkgRequest&quot;.  The
                response model is &quot;org.haiku.haikudepotserver.api1.model.pkg.GetPkgResult&quot;.  The
                actual server method that is invoked as a result of this request can be found at
                &quot;org.haiku.haikudepotserver.api1.PkgApi#getPkg(..)&quot;.
            </para>

            <para>
                You will notice at the top of this interface, there is an annotation that describes the path or
                &quot;endpoint&quot; for this API.  In this case it is &quot;/api/v1/pkg&quot;.  Given a host
                and port, this can be extrapolated into a URL that can be used to invoke to this method.
                An example would be &quot;http://localhost:8080/api/v1/pkg&quot;.
            </para>

            <para>
                The invocation is made using the HTTP protocol to such a URL with the method POST.  The Content-Type
                HTTP header must be set to &quot;application/json&quot; for both the request and the response.
                The request object would look something like this;
            </para>

            <para>
                <programlisting>{
  &quot;jsonrpc&quot;:&quot;2.0&quot;,
  &quot;id&quot;:4143431,
  &quot;method&quot;:&quot;getPkg&quot;,
  &quot;params&quot;:[{
    &quot;name&quot;:&quot;apr&quot;,
    &quot;architectureCode&quot;:&quot;x86&quot;,
    &quot;versionType&quot;:&quot;NONE&quot;
  }]
}</programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
                The &quot;id&quot; value here can be anything.  It must be supplied and is used to correlate a
                request with a response; the same &quot;id&quot; value that arrives in the request is relayed
                back in the response.  If a client were using the API in an asynchronous manner then being able
                to correlate the request and the response is very important.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                All going well, the following (abridged) form of response would be sent back to the client;
            </para>

            <para>
                <programlisting>{
  &quot;jsonrpc&quot;:&quot;2.0&quot;,
  &quot;id&quot;:4143431,
  &quot;result&quot;:{
    &quot;name&quot;:&quot;apr&quot;,
    &quot;hasIcon&quot;:true,
    &quot;canEdit&quot;:false,
    &quot;versions&quot;:[],
    &quot;modifyTimestamp&quot;:12345678
  }
}</programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
                See the
                <ulink url="http://www.jsonrpc.org">JSON-RPC</ulink>
                web site for examples of the response envelope format for the scenario in which an error has
                arisen in the invocation.
            </para>

        </example>

        <section>
            <title>Error Codes</title>

            <para>
                A set of known JSON-RPC error codes are agreed between the client and server.  See the JSON-RPC
                specification for known error codes used for transport-related issues such as invalid parameters.
                Application-specific error codes are documented in the java source at
                &quot;org.haiku.haikudepotserver.api1.support.Constants&quot;.
            </para>

            <para>
                Some errors such as the validation error (code -32800) may also carry additional data that provides
                detail as to the nature of the error that has arisen.  Java logic for assembling the error
                payloads can be found at &quot;org.haiku.haikudepotserver.api1.support.ErrorResolverImpl&quot;.
            </para>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>REST API</title>

        <para>
            REST API is generally required where data is inappropriate to encode as JSON-RPC.  This tends to be
            situations where the data is binary in nature.  An example of this is where a package icon needs
            to be uploaded.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Entry Point</title>

            <para>
                This API will provide the web application's HTML user interface.
            </para>

            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>GET</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Response Content-Type</term>
                        <listitem>text/html</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="api-importrepositorydata">
            <title>Import Repository Data</title>

            <para>
                This API provides a mechanism by which an external client is able to trigger the application to
                start importing package-related data from a remote repository.  This API is provided as REST
                because the client is likely to be scripted using a scripting language and REST is the most
                appropriate protocol to employ in this situation.  This invocation will trigger the import process,
                but the import process will execute in a background thread in the application server and will not
                block the client.
            </para>

            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>GET</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__repository/&lt;repositorycode&gt;/import</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__repository/&lt;repositorycode&gt;/source/&lt;repositorysourcecode&gt;/import</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Response Content-Type</term>
                        <listitem>text/plain</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Expected HTTP Status Codes</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>200</term>
                                    <listitem>The import job was accepted</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>404</term>
                                    <listitem>The repository or source was not able to be found.</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

            <para>
                An example URL is &quot;http://localhost:8080/repository/haikudepot/import&quot;
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Get Package Icon</title>
            <para>
                This API is able to provide the icon for a package.  If there is no icon stored then this method
                will provide a fall-back image if the &quot;f&quot; query parameter is configured to &quot;true&quot;
                &#x2014; otherwise it will return a 404 HTTP status code.  Providing a fallback image may not be
                possible in all cases.  The request will return a &quot;Last-Modified&quot; header.  The timestamps
                of this header will correlate to the &quot;modifyTimestamp&quot; that is provided in API responses
                such as &quot;GetPkResult&quot; and &quot;SearchPkgsResult&quot;.  The value for
                &quot;modifyTimestamp&quot; will be at millisecond resolution, but the HTTP headers will be at
                second resolution.  The path includes a &quot;mediatype-extension&quot; which can have one of the
                following values;
            </para>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>png</listitem>
                    <listitem>hvif</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>
                Details of the API;
            </para>

            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>GET, HEAD</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__pkgicon/&lt;pkgname&gt;.&lt;mediatype-extension&gt;</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Response Content-Type</term>
                        <listitem>&quot;image/png&quot; or &quot;application/x-vnd.haiku-icon&quot;</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Query Parameters</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>s</term>
                                    <listitem>Either 16 or 32 for the number of pixels; omitt for hivf files</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>f</term>
                                    <listitem>&quot;true&quot; will yield a fallback image in the response if possible</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Expected HTTP Status Codes</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>200</term>
                                    <listitem>The icon is provided in the response (for GET)</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>415</term>
                                    <listitem>The path did not include ".png" or the size is invalid</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>400</term>
                                    <listitem>The package name was not supplied</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>404</term>
                                    <listitem>The package was not found or no image was present</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

            <para>
                An example URL for obtaining a bitmap image would be
                &quot;http://localhost:8080/__pkgicon/apr.png?size=32&amp;f=true&quot;.
            </para>

            <para>
                An example URL for obtaining a Haiku vector image file image would be
                &quot;http://localhost:8080/__pkgicon/apr.hvif&quot;
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>

            <title>Get All Packages' Icons as an Archive</title>

            <para>
                This API is able to generate a &quot;tar-ball&quot; containing all of the icon data together
                with some meta-data about the icons.  Note that the data will be compressed using gzip
                compression.  After making this call, the client may be redirected to a different URL to
                actually access the data.  Clients should not make assumptions about the form of the redirected
                URL.
            </para>
            <para>
                This API supports the <link linkend="api-ifmodifiedsince">If-Modified-Since</link> header.
            </para>
            <para>
                The tar-ball contains a file &quot;info.json&quot; which has a field &quot;dataModifyTimestamp&quot;
                that can be used to form the &quot;If-Modified-Since&quot;.  Otherwise, the file contains each entry
                in the form &quot;hicn/&lt;package-name&gt;/&lt;icon-leaf&gt;.&lt;extension&gt;&quot;.  Possible
                values for the extension are;
            </para>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>png</listitem>
                    <listitem>hvif</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>
                The icon-leaf may be &quot;icon&quot; in the case of HVIF data or in the case of a bitmap icon,
                the icon-leaf will be the size of the image; for example 16, 32 or 64.
            </para>

            <para>
                Details of the API;
            </para>

            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>GET</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__pkgicon/all.tar.gz</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Expected HTTP Status Codes</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>302</term>
                                    <listitem>Redirect to the actual payload data.</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>304</term>
                                    <listitem>The data was not modified since the supplied timestamp.</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Get All Repositories' Details</title>

            <para>
                This API is able to generate a large JSON payload containing details regarding each active
                repository.  Note that the path contains a natural language code such as &quot;de&quot; but
                at the time of writing there is no support for localizing this information.
            </para>

            <para>
                This API supports the <link linkend="api-ifmodifiedsince">If-Modified-Since</link> header.
            </para>

            <para>
                Details of the API;
            </para>

            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>GET</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__repository/all_&lt;natural-language-code&gt;.json.gz</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Expected HTTP Status Codes</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>302</term>
                                    <listitem>Redirect to the actual payload data.</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>304</term>
                                    <listitem>The data was not modified since the supplied timestamp.</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Get Screenshot Image</title>

            <para>
                This API is able to produce an image for a screenshot.  The screenshot is identified in the path
                by its code.  The response will return a &quot;Last-Modified&quot; header.  The timestamps of
                this header will correlate to the &quot;modifyTimestamp&quot; that is provided in API responses
                such as &quot;GetPkResult&quot; and &quot;SearchPkgsResult&quot;.  The value for
                &quot;modifyTimestamp&quot; will be at millisecond resolution, but the HTTP headers will be at
                second resolution.  Requests for screenshot image should be accompanied by a target width and height.
                These values must be within a range of 1..1500.  The image will maintain its aspect ratio as it
                is scaled to fit within the supplied target width and height.
            </para>

            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>GET, HEAD</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__pkgscreenshot/&lt;screenshotcode&gt;.png</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Response Content-Type</term>
                        <listitem>&quot;image/png&quot;</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Query Parameters</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>tw</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        An integer value that describes the width that the image should be scaled to
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>th</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        An integer value that describes the height that the image should be scaled to
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Expected HTTP Status Codes</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>200</term>
                                    <listitem>The image data is provided in the response (for GET)</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>415</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        The path did not include &quot;.png&quot; or the target width or height
                                        is invalid or the length of the data is too large
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>400</term>
                                    <listitem>The screenshot code was not supplied</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>404</term>
                                    <listitem>The screenshot was not found</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

            <para>
                An example URL is
                &quot;http://localhost:8080/pkgscreenshot/a78hw20fh2p20fh122jd92.png?tw=640&amp;th=480&quot;.
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Get Raw Screenshot Image</title>

            <para>
                This API is able to provide the <emphasis>raw</emphasis> screenshot data.
            </para>

            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>GET</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__pkgscreenshot/&lt;screenshotcode&gt;/raw</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Response Content-Type</term>
                        <listitem>As per the stored data</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Expected HTTP Status Codes</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>200</term>
                                    <listitem>The image data is provided in the response</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>404</term>
                                    <listitem>The screenshot was not found for the code supplied</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

            <para>
                An example URL is &quot;http://localhost:8080/__pkgscreenshot/a78hw20fh2p20fh122jd92/raw&quot;.
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Add Screenshot Image</title>

            <para>
                This API is able to add an image as a screenshot for the nominated package.  The screenshot will
                be ordered last.  The payload of the POST must be a PNG image that is a maximum of 1500x1500
                pixels and a maximum of 2MB in size.
            </para>

            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>POST</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__pkgscreenshot/&lt;pkgname&gt;/add</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Query Parameters</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>format</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        The string &quot;png&quot; to define the image format.
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Expected HTTP Status Codes</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>200</term>
                                    <listitem>The screenshot image was stored</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>415</term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        The path did not include &quot;.png&quot; or the size (pixels or data) of
                                        the image is invalid or the payload is not PNG image data.
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>404</term>
                                    <listitem>The package identified in the path was not able to be found</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>400</term>
                                    <listitem>The package name was not supplied</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Specific Response Headers</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>X-HaikuDepotServer-ScreenshotCode</term>
                                    <listitem>Supplies the code of the newly created screenshot.</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

            <para>
                An example URL is &quot;http://localhost:8080/__pkgscreenshot/apr/add?format=png&quot;.
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Medium-Term Maintenance</title>

            <para>
                Medium-term maintenance includes tasks that should be undertaken every hour or so that clean-up
                disused resources.  An example is removing expired password-reset tokens from the database.
                Medium-term maintenance is triggered externally (from a process such as &quot;cron&quot;)
                rather than on an internal scheduler in order to simplify a multi-instance deployment.
            </para>


            <para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>HTTP Method</term>
                        <listitem>GET</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__maintenance/hourly</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Path</term>
                        <listitem>/__maintenance/daily</listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term>Expected HTTP Status Codes</term>
                        <listitem>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>200</term>
                                    <listitem>The maintenance request was accepted</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term>*</term>
                                    <listitem>The maintenance job was not accepted</listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </para>

        </section>

    </section>

</chapter>
